So my grandfather told me when I was a little girl,
إذَا حدثني جدي عندما كنت طفلةً صغيرة
"If you say a word often enough, it becomes you."
"إذا قلتِ الكلمة مرارًا بما فيه الكفاية ستصبح من طبيعتك."
And having grown up in a segregated city, Baltimore, Maryland,
وبعد ان كبرتُ في مدينة معزولة , بالتيمور, مريلاند
I sort of use that idea to go around America with a tape recorder --
استخدمت نوعا ما تلك الفكرة للتجوال حول امريكا مع اداة تسجيل--
thank God for technology --
الحمدلله على التكنولوجيا--
to interview people, thinking that if I walked in their words --
لمقابلة الناس, معتقدة ذلك انني اذا مشيت داخل كلماتهم--
which is also why I don't wear shoes when I perform --
والذي هو ايضًا سبب عدم ارتدائي للاحذية عندما اؤدي عرضا--
if I walked in their words, that I could sort of absorb America.
أنني إذا مشيت داخل كلماتهم لأمكنني نوع ما ان استوعب امريكا
I was also inspired by Walt Whitman,
كما الهمني أيضًا والت وايتمان
who wanted to absorb America and have it absorb him.
الذي اراد ان يستوعب امريكا وان يجعلها تستوعبه
So these four characters are going to be from that work
إذًا هذه الأربعة شخصيات ستكون من ذاك العمل
that I've been doing for many years now,
الذي قمت به لسنوات عديدة الاّن
and well over, I don't know, a couple of thousand people
وكثيرة جدًا-- لاأعلم لربما بضعة من ألاف الناس
I've interviewed.
اجريت معهم مقابلات
Anybody out here old enough to know Studs Terkel, that old radio man?
ايوجد بينكم شخص كبير بمافيه الكفاية ليتعرف على ستودس تركل, رجل الإذاعة القديم؟
So I thought he would be the perfect person
إذَا فكرت انه سيكون الشخص المناسب
to go to to ask about a defining moment in American history.
للسؤال عن لحظة حاسمة في التاريخ الأمريكي
You know, he was "born in 1912, the year the Titanic sank,
كما تعلمون, لقد ولد في عام 1912, االعام الذي غرقت فيه التايتنيك,
greatest ship every built. Hits the tip of an iceberg,
اعظم سفينة قط بنيت واصطدمت بطرف جبل جليد
and bam, it went down. It went down and I came up. Wow, some century."
و بام ذهبت للقاع, ذهبت للأسفل, وارتفعتُ انا للأعلى, واو ياله من قرن
(Laughter)
( ضحك)
So this is his answer about a defining moment in American history.
إذًا هذا هو جوابه عن اللحظة الحاسمة في التاريخ الأمريكي
"Defining moment in American history, I don't think there's one;
لحظة حاسمة في التاريخ الأمريكي, لا أعتقد ان هنالك واحدة
you can't say Hiroshima, that's a big one --
لايمكننا ان نقول ان هيروشيما كانت لحظة كبيرة--
I can't think of any one moment I would say is a defining moment.
لايمكنني التفكير في اية لحظة استطيع ان اقول انها حاسمة
The gradual slippage -- 'slippage' is the word
الإنزلاق التدريجي-- كلمة انزلاق
used by the people in Watergate, moral slippage --
استخدمها الناس في واترغايت, الإنزلاق الأخلاقي--
it's a gradual kind of thing, combination of things.
أنه من نوع الأشياء التدريجية, عبارة عن مجموعة من الأشياء
You see, we also have the technology.
كما ترون, نحن ايضًا لدينا التكنولوجيا
I say, less and less the human touch.
سأخبركم معها ستقل ثم تقل اللمسة الإنسانية
"Oh, let me kind of tell you a funny little play bit.
اه, دعوني اخبركم بطريقتي عن مسرحية مرحة قصيرة
The Atlanta airport is a modern airport,
مطار اتلانطا, هو مطار حديث
and they should leave the gate there.
يتوجب عليهم مغادرة البوابة هنالك
These trains that take you out to a concourse and on to a destination.
هذه القطارت التي تأخذك الى المحطات العامة وإلى اتجاهات معينة
And these trains are smooth,
تجدها انسيابية
and they're quiet and they're efficient.
هادئة وعملية
And there's a voice on the train, you know the voice was a human voice.
كما هنالك صوت داخل القطار, كما تعرفون انه صوت بشري
You see in the old days we had robots, robots imitated humans.
كما ترون في الأيام الخوالي كان لدينا رجال اّلييون يحاكون البشر
Now we have humans imitating robots.
اما الاّن فلدينا بشر يحاكون الرجال الأليين
So we got this voice on this train: Concourse One: Omaha, Lincoln.
إذَا جاءنا هذا الصوت من داخل القطار: المحطة الأولى: اوماها, لينكولن
Concourse Two: Dallas, Fort Worth. Same voice.
المحطة الثانية: دالاس, فورت ورث, نفس الصوت
Just as a train is about to go, a young couple rush in
و فقط عندما كان القطار بصدد المغادرة, زوجان شابان يهمان بالركوض
and they're just about to close the pneumatic doors.
الأبواب الهوائية بصدد الإغلاق الأن
And that voice, without losing a beat, says,
ويأتي ذلك الصوت من دون ان يفقد نبرة واحدة قائلاً
'Because of late entry, we're delayed 30 seconds.'
" لأجل صعود متأخرسنتعطل ل30 ثانية"
Just then, everybody's looking at this couple with hateful eyes
وقتها فقط ينظر الجميع لهذين الزوجين بنظرة بغض
and the couple's going like this, you know, shrinking.
ثم يصبح حالهم كما تعلمون خجلين
Well, I'd happened to have had a couple of drinks before boarding --
حسنًأ, حدث وقتها انني تناولت بعض الشراب قبل الصعود--
I do that to steel my nerves -- and so
فعلت ذلك لأقوي اعصابي-- و بالتالي
I imitate a train call, holding my hand on my --
قمت بمحاكاةِ احدى نداءات القطار, واضعتًأ يدي--
'George Orwell, your time has come,' you see.
" جورج اوريل, وقتك قد حان," ترون.
Well, some of you are laughing. Everybody laughs
حسنًا , بعضكم يضحك. الكل يضحك
when I say that, but not on this train. Silence.
عندما اروي تلك القصة, لكن ليس داخل ذاك القطار. صمت تام.
And so suddenly they're looking at me.
و إذًا فجأةً, الجميع ينظر إلي
So here I am with the couple, the three of us
وإذًا ها أنذا مع الشابين , ثلاثتنا فقط
shrinking at the foot of Calvary about to be up, you know.
محرجين عند جبهة المواجهة وبإستعداد للهروب,كما تعلمون
"Just then I see a baby, a little baby in the lap of a mother.
وقتها فقط رأيت, طفلاً رضيعًا فوق حجر و الدته.
I know it's Hispanic because she's speaking Spanish to her companion.
اعلم انه من أصل لاتيني لان والدته تتحدث الأسبانية مع رفيقتها
So I'm going to talk to the baby. So I say to the baby,
إذَا سأتحدث إلى الصغير, إذا ساقول للصغير
holding my hand over my mouth because my breath must be 100 proof,
قابضتًا يدي فوق فمي, لأن رائحة نفسي لابد ان تكون كـ 100 برهان
I say to the baby, 'Sir or Madam,
اقول للرضيع, " سيدي او سيدتي,
what is your considered opinion of the human species?'
ما رأيك المعتبر في فصيلة البشر؟"
And the baby looks, you know, the way babies look at you clearly,
و يينظر إلي الرضيع, تعرفون, الرضع ينظرون إليك بوضوح,
starts laughing,
يبدأ بالضحك,
starts busting out with this crazy little laugh.
ثم ينفجر في تلك الضحكة الصغيرة المجنونة.
I say, 'Thank God for a human reaction, we haven't lost yet.'
فأقول: " الحمدلله لردة فعل انسانية, نحن لم نفقدها بعد."
"But you see, the human touch, you see, it's disappearing.
لكن كما ترون, اللمسة الإنسانية, إنها تختفي
You know, you see, you've got to question the official truth.
كما تعلمون, يجب عليكم اختبار الحقيقة الرسمية
You know the thing that was so great about Mark Twain --
أتعلمون اعظم شيئ عن مارك توين--
you know we honor Mark Twain, but we don't read him.
تعلمون اننا نفتخر به, لكننا لانقرأ له
We read 'Huck Finn,' of course, we read 'Huck Finn' of course.
أ نقرأ لهاك فين, بالتأكيد نحن نقرأ لهاك فين
I mean, Huck, of course, was tremendous.
اقصد ان هاك , بالـتأكيد كان رائعًا.
Remember that great scene on the raft, remember what Huck did?
تذكرون ذلك المشهد العظيم من العوامة , اتذكرون ماذا فعل هاك؟
You see, here's Huck; he's an illiterate kid; he's had no schooling,
ترون, هاهنا هاك, صبي امي, لم يتحصل على اية تعليم
but there's something in him.
لكن هنالك شيء فيه.
And the official truth, the truth was, the law was,
والحقيقة الرسمية, الحقيقة, والقانون كانت
that a black man was a property, was a thing, you see.
ان الزنجي كان مملوكًأ, كان كالمتاع, كما ترون
And Huck gets on the raft with a property named Jim, a slave, see.
ركب هاك داخل العوامة بصحبة متاع او عبد, يدعى جيم, اترون
And he hears that Jim is going to go and take his wife and kids
ثم يسمع ان جيم سوف يرحل ويأخذ معه زوجته وأطفاله
and steal them from the woman who owns them,
ويسرقهم من المرأة التي تمتلكهم,
and Huck says, 'Ooh, oh my God, ooh, ooh --
فيقول هاك, " اوه اوه ياإلهي, اوه اوه--
that woman, that woman never did anybody any harm.
تلك المرأة, لم تسيئ لأحدٍ قط
Ooh, he's going to steal; he's going to steal;
أوه, سوف يسرق, سوف يسرق,
he's going to do a terrible thing.'
سوف يقوم بشيء فظيع."
Just then, two slavers caught up, guys chasing slaves, looking for Jim.
وقتها فقط, تاجران رقيق ألتقيا بعض الأشخاص الذين يطاردون العبيد, بحثَأ عن جيم.
'Anybody up on that raft with you?' Huck says, 'Yeah.'
" هل هنالك اية شخص فوق هذه العوامة معكم؟" يجيب هاك, " نعم."
'Is he black or white?' 'White.' And they go off.
" هل هو اسود ام أبيض؟" " ابيض" فيذهبون عنهم
And Huck said, 'Oh my God, oh my God, I lied, I lied, ooh,
و يقول هاك, " اوه ياإلهي, اوه ياإلهي, لقد كذبت, لقد كذبت, اوه,
I did a terrible thing, did a terrible thing -- why do I feel so good?'
لقد فعلت شيئًا فظيعًا, لقد فعلت شيئًا فظيعًأ -- لماذا احس بالراحة؟"
"But it's the goodness of Huck, that stuff that Huck's been made of,
لكنها طيبة هاك, التي خلق منها
you see, all been buried; it's all been buried.
كما ترون, كلهم دفنوا, جميعهم دفنوا.
So the human touch, you see, it's disappearing.
إذًا كما ترون المسة الإنسانية تختفي
So you ask about a defining moment --
إذَا أتسألون عن اللحظة الحاسمة
ain't no defining moment in American history for me.
ليست هنالك لحظة حاسمة في التاريخ الأمريكي بالنسبة لي.
It's an accretion of moments that add up to where we are now,
انها تضاخم لمجموعة لحظات تضيف إلى أين نحن اليوم
where trivia becomes news.
عندما تصبح توافه الأمور اخبارًا
And more and more, less and less awareness of the pain of the other.
و كما تزداد وتزداد, يقل ويقل وعينا بألاّم الأخرين.
Huh. You know, I don't know if you could use this or not,
اّاه,أ تعلمون, لأعرف إذا كان بإمكانكم استخدام هذه
but I was quoting Wright Morris, a writer from Nebraska, who says,
لكن كنت اقتبس من رايت موريس, كاتب من نيبراسكا, والذي يقول
'We're more and more into communications
كلما ازداد ولعنا بالإتصال
and less and less into communication.'
كلما قل تواصلنا
Okay, kids, I got to scram, got to go see my cardiologist."
حسنًا ياصغار, علي ان اغادر لمقابلة طبيب القلب
And that's Studs Terkel.
انه ستود تركل
(Applause)
( تصفيق)
So, talk about risk taking. I'm going to do somebody that nobody likes.
إذًا بالحديث عن المجازفة, علي ان اودي شخصية لايحبها الكثير.
You know, most actors want to do characters that are likeable --
كما تعلمون معظم الممثلين يحبون تأدية الأدوار المحبوبة--
well, not always, but the notion, especially at a conference like this,
حسنًا, ليس دائمًا, لكن الغالبية بالأخص في مؤتمر كهذا,
I like to inspire people.
احب ان الهم الناس
But since this was called "risk taking,"
لكن بما أن القيام بهذا يعتبر مجازفة
I'm doing somebody who I never do, because she's so unlikeable
سأقدم شخصية لم يؤدها احد من قبل لأنها غير محبوبة
that one person actually came backstage
في الحقيقة هذه الشخصية اتتني خلف الكواليس
and told me to take her out of the show she was in.
وحدثتني انه علي اخذها خارج العرض الذي كانت فيه
And I'm doing her because I think we think of risk,
وسأؤديها لأننا نفكر في المجازفة
at a conference like this, as a good thing.
في مؤتمر كهذا, كشيء جيد
But there are certain other connotations to the word "risk,"
لكن هنالك دلالات اخرى لكلمة مجازفة
and the same thing about the word "nature." What is nature?
ونفس الشيئ عن كلمة طبيعة, ماهي الطبيعة؟
Maxine Greene, who's a wonderful philosopher
ماكساين غرين, والتي هي فيلسوفة رائعة
who's as old as Studs, and was the head of a philosophy --
كما انها طاعنة في السن كستودس, وكانت رئيسة الفيلُسوفي --
great, big philosophy kind of an organization --
منظمة كبيرة وعظيمة للفلسفة,
I went to her and asked her what are the two things
ذهبت إليها وسألتها ما الشيئين
that she doesn't know, that she still wants to know.
اللذا ن تجهلهما, وتود ان تتعرف عليهما.
And she said, "Well, personally, I still feel like I have to curtsey
فأجابتني, " حسنًا, شخصيًا, مازلت اشعر انه علي الإنحناء
when I see the president of my university.
عندما أرى رئيس جامعتي.
And I still feel as though I've got to get coffee
وأيضًا مازلت اشعر انه يتوجب علي ان أٌحضر القهوة
for my male colleagues, even though I've outlived most of them."
لزملائي الذكور, بالرغم من انني عشت اطول منهم
And she said, "And then intellectually,
وقالت, " وعلى الصعيد الثقافي
I don't know enough about the negative imagination.
لا أعرف الكثير عن التخيل السلبي.
And September 11th certainly taught us
و الحادي عشر من سيبتمبر حتمًا علمنا
that that's a whole area we don't investigate."
ان تلك منطقة كاملة لا نتقصى عنها."
So this piece is about a negative imagination.
إذًا هذه المقطوعة ستكون عن التخيل السلبي.
It raises questions about what nature is, what Mother Nature is,
ستطرح اسئلة عن ماهية الطبيعة, وما هي الطبيعة الأم,
and about what a risk can be.
وكيف يمكن ان يكون الخطر
And I got this in the Maryland Correctional Institute for Women.
تحصلت على هذه القطعة من المؤسسة الإصلاحية للنساء في ميريلاند
Everything I do is word for word off a tape.
كل شيء افعله, هو كلمة مسجلة داخل شريط
And I title things because I think people speak in organic poems,
واعنون الأشياء لأنني اظن ان الناس يتحدثون في قصائد عضوية
and this is called "A Mirror to Her Mouth."
وهذه تسمى: " مراّة لفمها"
And this is an inmate named Paulette Jenkins.
وهذه ستكون عن سجينة تدعى بوليت جينكيز
"I began to learn how to cover it up,
" تعلمت كيف اخبئها"
because I didn't want nobody to know that this was happening in my home.
لأنني لم أرد لأحد ان يتعرف على ماكان يحدث داخل منزلي.
I want everybody to think we were a normal family.
اردت ان يظن الجميع اننا عائلة طبيعية.
I mean we had all the materialistic things,
اقصد اننا كان لدينا كل الأشياء المادية
but that didn't make my children pain any less;
لكن ذلك لم يجعل ألم صغاري اقل:
that didn't make their fears subside.
لم يجعل ذلك مخاوفهم تهدأ.
I ran out of excuses about how we got black eyes
نفذت كل أعذاري لإخبارهم كيف اسودت اعيننا
and busted lips and bruises. I didn't had no more excuses.
ولماذا شفاهنا ملكومة, وتغطينا الكدمات, لم امتلك اية اعذار
And he beat me too. But that didn't change the fact
و أوسعني ضربًا أيضًا, لكن ذلك لم يغير حقيقة
that it was a nightmare for my family; it was a nightmare.
أنه كان كابوسًا لعائلتي, كان كابوس.
And I failed them dramatically,
وانني خذلتهم بشدة,
because I allowed it to go on and on and on.
لأنني تركت الموضوع يستمر ويستمر
"But the night that Myesha got killed --
لكن الليلة التي قتلت فيها مايشا--
and the intensity just grew and grew and grew,
والحدة التي نمت ونمت ونمت,
until one night we came home from getting drugs,
إلى ان أتت ليلة عودنا فيها إلى المنزل بعد تعاطي المخدرات
and he got angry with Myesha, and he started beating her,
و ثار غضبه على مايشا, وبدأ بضربها
and he put her in a bathtub. Oh, he would use a belt.
ثم وضعها داخل حوض الإستحمام, اه ولم يتوانى عن استخدام الحزام
He had a belt because he had this warped perverted thing
استخدم الحزام لأنه كانت لديه تلك الفكرة المشوهه المنحرفه
that Myesha was having sex with her little brother
والتي هي أن مايشا كانت على علاقة جنسية مع أخيها الصغير
and they was fondling each other -- that would be his reason.
وانهما كانا يلاطفان بعضهما البعض-- كان ذلك سببه
I'm just talking about the particular night that she died.
انني فقط اتحدث عن الليلة التي توفيت فيها
And so he put her in the bathtub,
و إذَا وضعها داخل حوض الإستحمام
and I was in the bedroom with the baby.
وكنت في غرفة النوم مع الصغير
"And four months before this happened, four months before Myesha died,
وفي فترة الأربعة اشهر قبل ان يحدث هذا, أربعة اشهر قبل ان تتوفي مايشا
I thought I could really fix this man. So I had a baby by him -- insane --
اعتقدت انه كان بإمكاني تغيره, إذَا انجبت طفلاً منه -- ياله من جنون--
thinking that if I gave him his own kid, he would leave mine alone.
معتقدةً انني اذا اعطيته طفله الخاص, فأنه سيدع طفلتي لحالها.
And it didn't work, didn't work.
ولكن لم تنجح محاولتي, لم تنجح
And I ended up with three children, Houston, Myesha and Dominic,
و أنتهيت بثلاثة اطفال, هوستن, مايشا, ودومينيك
who was four months old when I came to jail.
الذي كان عمره اربعة اشهر عندما دخلت السجن
"And I was in the bedroom. Like I said, he had her in the bathroom
وكنت داخل غرفة النوم كما اخبرتكم, واخذها الى الحمام
and he -- he -- every time he hit her, she would fall.
و -- وفي كل مرةٍ يضربها, كانت تقع
And she would hit her head on the tub. It happened continuously, repeatedly.
و كان رأسها يرتطم بالحوض مرارًا وتكرارًا.
I could hear it, but I dared not to move. I didn't move.
كان بإمكاني سماعه, لكن لم اقوى على الحركة, لم اتحرك.
I didn't even go and see what was happening.
حتى أنني لم اذهب لأرى ماكان يحدث
I just sat there and listened.
جلست هنالك فقط واستمعت
And then he put her in the hallway.
وبعد ذلك وضعها في الممر
He told her, just set there. And so she set there for about four or five hours.
اخبرها اجلسي فقط هاهنا, وجلست هنالك لفترة اربعة لخمسة ساعات.
And then he told her, get up.
وبعدها اخبرها بأن تنهض.
And when she got up, she says she couldn't see.
وعندما نهضت, قالت انها لاتستطيع الرؤية
Her face was bruised. She had a black eye.
وجهها كان متكدمًا وعينها كانت سوداء
All around her head was just swollen;
رأسها كان متورمًا
her head was about two sizes of its own size.
رأسها كان ضعفي حجمه الطبيعي
I told him, 'Let her go to sleep.' He let her go to sleep.
اخبرته دعها تذهب لتنام, تركها تذهب للنوم
"The next morning she was dead.
في الصباح اللاحق توفيت
He went in to check on her for school, and he got very excited.
ذهب ليوقظها للمدرسة, و أصبح متحمسًا جدًا
He says, 'She won't breathe.'
اخبرني أنها لن تتنفس
I knew immediately that she was dead.
عرفت مباشرةً انها ماتت
I didn't even want to accept the fact that she was dead, so I went in
لم اريد حتى ان اتقبل حقيقة موتها, فذهبت
and I put a mirror to her mouth --
ووضعت مراّة فوق فمها--
there was no thing, nothing, coming out of her mouth.
لم يكن هنالك اية شيء يخرج من فمها
He said, he said, he said,
قال, قال, قال
'We can't, we can't let nobody find out about this.'
ليس بإمكننا ان نترك اية احد ليعرف ماحدث
He say, 'You've got to help me.' I agree. I agree.
اخبرني, عليك ان تساعديني, أوافق, أوافق
"I mean, I've been keeping a secret for years and years and years,
اعني, لقد كتمت السر لسنين وسنين وسنين
so it just seemed like second hand to me, just to keep on keeping it a secret.
إذَا كانت كيد اخرى أمدها, لأستمر في كتمان السر
So we went to the mall and we told a police that we had, like, lost her,
إذَا ذهبنا للسوق وأخبرنا الشرطي كأننا فقدناها
that she was missing.
أنها كانت مفقودة
We told a security guard that she was missing,
اخبرنا حارس الأمن انها كانت مفقودة
though she wasn't missing.
بالرغم من انها لم تكن مفقودة
And we told the security guard what we had put on her
كما اخبرنا رجل الأمن بهيئة الملابس التي وضعناها عليها
and we went home and we dressed her in exactly the same thing
ثم ذهبنا إلى المنزل و ألبسناها تفس الشيئ
that we had told the security guard that we had put on her.
الذي اخبرنا رجل الأمن انها كانت ترتديه
"And then we got the baby and my other child,
وبعدها أخذنا الرضيع وطفلي الأخر
and we drove out to, like, I-95.
وتوجهنا جميعًا الى الخط السريع 1-95
I was so petrified and so numb,
كنت مشلولة من الخوف مصابة بالخدر
all I could look was in the rear-view mirror.
كل ماكان بإستطاعتي فعله كان النظر إلى المرأة الخلفية
And he just laid her right on the shoulder of the highway.
ثم اخذها ووضعها على حافة الخط السريع
My own child, I let that happen to."
تركت ذلك يحدث لطفلتي
So that's an investigation of the negative imagination.
إذُا كان هذا استقصاءًا عن التخيل السلبي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
When I started this project
عندما بدأت هذا المشروع
called "On the Road: A Search For an American Character"
المعروف على الطريق: بحث لإيجاد الشخصية الأمريكية
with my tape recorder, I thought that I was going to go around America
مع اّلة التسجيل, اعتقدت انني سأتجول حول امريكا
and find it in all its aspects -- bull riders, cowboys, pig farmers,
واتعرف عليها من جميع جوانبها-- مصارعوا ثيران, رعاة ابقار, ومزارعوا خنازير
drum majorettes -- but I sort of got tripped on race relations,
قارعوا طبول-- لكن نوع الما علقت داخل العلاقات بين الأعراق
because my first big show was a show about a race riot.
لأن أول عرض تلفزيوني كبير اقدمه كان عن الإضطرابات العرقية
And so I went to both -- two race riots,
وإذًا قمت بتقديم اضطرابيين عرقيين
one of which was the Los Angeles riot. And this next piece is from that.
احدهما كان أضطراب لوس انجلس, والمقطوعة القادمة ستكون منه
Because this is what I would say
لأنه يسعني ان اقول هذا
I've learned the most about race relations, from this piece.
لقد تعلمت الكثير عن العلاقات بين الأعراق, من هذه المقطوعة
It's a kind of an aria, I would say, and in many tapes that I have.
يمكنني ان اقول انها كنغمة خاصة, موجودة في مجموعة من الأشرطة التي امتلكها
Everybody knows that the Los Angeles riots happened
كل شخص يعلم ان اضطراب لوس انجلس قد حدث
because four cops beat up a black man named Rodney King.
لأن أربعة شرطيين قاموا بضرب رجل اسود يدعى رودني كينغ
It was captured on videotape -- technology --
تم تصوير الإعتداء في شريط فيديو -- تكنولوجيا--
and it was played all over the world.
وتم بثه حول العالم جميعًا
Everybody thought the four cops would go to jail.
الجميع اعتقد انه لابد ان يسجن الأربعةٌ شرطيين
They did not, so there were riots.
لكنهم لم يسجنوا, فحدث الإضطراب
And what a lot of people forget, is there was a second trial,
و مانسيه الجميع , انه كان هنالك محاكمة أخرى
ordered by George Bush, Sr.
بأمر جورج بوش الأب
And that trial came back with two cops going to jail
ونتجت المحاكمة عن سجن شرطيين
and two cops declared innocent. I was at that trial.
اما الأخرين فقد اعلنت برأتهما, كنت داخل المحاكمة
And I mean, the people just danced in the streets
و اقصد ان الجميع رقصوا فقط على الطرقات
because they were afraid there was going to be another riot.
لأنهم خافوا انه سيحدث اضطراب أخر
Explosion of joy that this verdict had come back this way.
انبثقت بهجة عارمة لصدور الحكم الثاني
So there was a community that didn't -- the Korean-Americans,
إلا ان مجتمعًا اخر لم يسعد -- انهم الكوريون الأمريكيون,
whose stores had been burned to the ground.
الذين احرقت متاجهرهم حتى الأرض
And so this woman, Mrs. Young-Soon Han,
و إذا السيدة, يونغ-سُون هَـن,
I suppose will have taught me the most that I have learned about race.
افترض انها اكثر شخصية علمتني عن العنصرية
And she asks also a question that Studs talks about:
كما انها طرحت سؤالاً تحدث عنه ستودس:
this notion of the "official truth," to question the "official truth."
تلك النظرية عن الحقيقة الرسمية, وأنه علينا اختبارها.
So what she's questioning here, she's taking a chance
إذَا مالذي تتسأل عنه هاهنا, أنها ستستغل الفرصة
and questioning what justice is in society.
لتتسأل عن معنى العدالة في المجتمع
And this is called, "Swallowing the Bitterness."
و هذه تدعى "تجرع المرارة"
"I used to believe America was the best.
كنت اعتقد ان امريكا هي الأفضل
I watched in Korea many luxurious Hollywood lifestyle movie.
شاهدت في كوريا العديد من افلام هوليود والتي تتسم بطابع الرفاهية في الحياة
I never saw any poor man, any black.
لم اشاهد قط اية رجل فقير, او رجل اسود
Until 1992, I used to believe America was the best -- I still do;
حتى عام 1992, كنت اعتقد ان امريكا هي الأفضل-- ومازلت
I don't deny that because I am a victim.
لا أنكر هذا لأنني ضحية
But at the end of '92, when we were in such turmoil,
لكن نهاية 92, عندما كنا في ذلك الإضطراب
and having all the financial problems, and all the mental problems,
نعاني من كل المشاكل المادية و النفسية
I began to really realize that Koreans
بدأت حقيقة انتبه لأن الكوريون
are completely left out of this society and we are nothing.
نبذوا كليًا من المجتمع, وأننا لانعني شيئًا
Why? Why do we have to be left out?
لماذا؟ لماذا يجب ان ننبذ؟
We didn't qualify for medical treatment, no food stamp, no GR,
نحن لم نستحق خدمات العلاج, او الطعام المدعوم, او حتى GR
no welfare, anything. Many African-Americans who never work
ولا حتى خدمات إجتماعية, او اي شيئ. العديد من الامريكان الأفارقة الذين لايعملون
got minimum amount of money to survive.
تحصلوا على حد ادنى من المال ليساعدهم على الحياة
We didn't get any because we have a car and a house.
نحن لم نتحصل على شيئ لأننا نعمل, ولدينا سيارة ومنزل.
And we are high taxpayer. Where do I find justice?
وندفع مبالغ عالية من الضرائب, اين اجد العدل؟
"OK. OK? OK. OK.
حسنًا, حسنًأ, حسنًا
Many African-Americans probably think that they won by the trial.
العديد من الأمريكان الأفارقة يظنون انهم ربحوا عن طريق المحكمة
I was sitting here watching them the morning after the verdict,
كنت جالست هاهنا اشاهدهم في الصباح بعد الحكم
and all the day they were having a party, they celebrated,
فد احتفلوا طوال اليوم
all of South Central, all the churches. And they say,
كل الجنوب المتوسط, وكل الكنائس, ويقولون
'Well, finally justice has been done in this society.'
حسنًا, اخيرًا قد تم تطبيق العدل في هذا المجتمع
Well, what about victims' rights?
إذَا ماذا عن حقوق ضحايا الإضطراب؟
They got their rights by destroying innocent Korean merchants.
لقد تحصلوا على حقهم بعد ان افسدوا بضائع الكوريين المساكين
They have a lot of respect, as I do, for Dr. Martin King.
يحترمون كثيراً دكتور مارتن كينغ, كما أحترمه
He is the only model for black community; I don't care Jesse Jackson.
هو المثال الوحيد لمجتمع السود, لا يهم جسي جاكسون أيضًا
He is the model of non-violence, non-violence --
هو مثال اللاعُنف, اللاعُنف--
and they would all like to be in his spirit.
وهم جميعًا يحبون ان يكونوا على نفس أخلاقه
"But what about 1992? They destroyed innocent people.
لكن ماذا عن 1992؟ لقد اعتدوا على اناس بريئين
And I wonder if that is really justice
و أتعجب إن كان هذا حقًا عدل
for them, to get their rights in that way.
عندما يتحصلوا على حقوقهم بهذه الطريقة
I was swallowing the bitterness, sitting here alone and watching them.
كنت اتجرع المرارة, جالسة هاهنا وحيدة اراقبهم
They became so hilarious, but I was happy for them.
لقد كانوا مضحكين جدًا لكنني سعيدة لأجلهم
I was glad for them. At least they got something back, OK.
لقد كنت سعيدة لهم على الأقل هم حصلوا على شئ في المقابل, حسنًا
Let's just forget about Korean victims and other victims
دعونا ننسى الضحايا الكوريين و بقية الضحايا الأخرين
who were destroyed by them.
الذين دمروا بسببهم
They fought for their rights for over two centuries,
لقد حاربوا لحقوقهم مايفوت القرنين
and maybe because they sacrifice other minorities,
وربما لأنهم ضحوا بالأقليات الأخرى
Hispanic, Asian, we would suffer more in the mainstream.
الأسبان, الأسيوين, يجب علينا ان نعاني اكثر في الشارع العام.
That's why I understand;
لأجل ذلك اتفهم
that's why I have a mixed feeling about the verdict.
مشاعري المختلطة تجاه الحكم
"But I wish that, I wish that, I wish that
لكنني اتمنى , أتمنى, أتمنى
I could be part of the enjoyment.
لو كان بإستطاعاتي أن اكون جزءًا من تلك الفرحة
I wish that I could live together with black people.
اتمنى لوكان بمقدوري ان اعيش مع السود
But after the riot, it's too much difference.
لكن بعد احداث الشغب اختلف الأمر
The fire is still there. How do you say it? [Unclear].
مازالت النار هنالك. كيف تقولونها؟ [غير واضحة]
Igniting, igniting, igniting fire. Igniting fire.
تشتعل, تشتعل, نار مشتعلة, نار مشتعلة
It's still there; it can burst out anytime."
مازالت هنالك بإمكانها ان تنفجر في اية وقت
Mrs. Young-Soon Han.
السيدة يونغ- سون هان
(Applause)
( تصفيق)
The other reason that I don't wear shoes
السبب الأخر لعدم ارتدائي للأحذية
is just in case I really feel like I have to cuddle up
في حالة انني شعرت انني ساعانق شخصية اخرى
and get into the feet of somebody,
واقف على قدميها
walking really in somebody else's shoes.
ان امشي داخل حذاء شخصٍ أخر
And I told you that in -- you know, I didn't give you the year,
اخبرتكم حدث ذلك في-- تعلمون انني لم اعطكم العام
but in '79 I thought that I was going to go around
لكن في عام 79 اعتقدت انه كان بإمكاني التجول
and find bull riders and pig farmers and people like that,
لأجد مصارعي ثيران, وأصحاب مزارع الخنازير, واشخاص على شاكلتهم
and I got sidetracked on race relations.
وانحرفت عن مسار علاقات الاعراق
Finally, I did find a bull rider, two years ago.
أخيرًا, قمت بإيجاد متصارع ثيران, قبل عامين
And I've been going to the rodeos with him, and we've bonded.
وصرت اذهب إلى حلقات المصارعة معه, وتوطدت علاقتنا
And he's the lead in an op-ed I did about the Republican Convention.
و صار مقدمة كود التعريف الشخصي الذي اجريته عن المعاهدة الجمهورية
He's a Republican -- I won't say anything about my party affiliation, but anyway --
انه جمهوري-- ولن اقول شيئًا عن ارتباطي الحزبي, لكن بطريقة ما
so this is my dear, dear Brent Williams,
هو عزيزي برنت ويليامز,
and this is on toughness,
وهذا الموضوع عن القسوة
in case anybody needs to know about being tough
في حالة اراد احدكم ان يتعلم كيف بإمكانه ان يكون قاسيًا
for the work that you do. I think there's a real lesson in this.
في العمل الذي يؤديه, اعتقد ان هنلك عبرة حقيقة من خلال هذه القصة
And this is called "Toughness."
وهذه تسمى " قسوة"
"Well, I'm an optimist. I mean basically I'm an optimist.
حسنًا, انني متفائل, اقصد في الأساس انني مثفائل
I mean, you know, I mean, it's like my wife, Jolene,
اعني, كما تعرفون, اقصد أنها كزوجتي جولين
her family's always saying,
عائلتها دائمًا تقول
you know, you ever think he's just a born loser?
تعرفون, نعتقد اكثر من اية وقت مضى انه ولد خاسرًا
It seems like he has so much bad luck, you know.
يبدوا كأن لديه الكثير من سؤء الحظ,كما تعلمون
But then when that bull stepped on my kidney, you know,
لكن الأن عندما طعنني ذلك الثور في كليتي, تعرفون
I didn't lose my kidney -- I could have lost my kidney,
انني لم اخسر كليتي-- كان بإستطاعتي خسارتها
I kept my kidney, so I don't think I'm a born loser.
حافظت على كليتي, حتى لا أعتقد انني ولدت خاسرًا
I think that's good luck.
اعتقد ان هذا من حسن الحظ
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"And, I mean, funny things like this happen.
واعني اشياء مرحة كهذه تحدث
I was in a doctor's office last CAT scan,
كنت داخل مكتب الطبيب في اخر صورة مقطعية لي
and there was a Reader's Digest, October 2002.
وكان هنالك ريدرز دايجست , عدد اكتوبر 2002
It was like, 'seven ways to get lucky.' And it says
كان, يعرض سبعة طرق لأن تكون محظوظًأ, والتي تقول
if you want to get lucky,
إذا اردت ان تصبح محظوظًا
you know, you've got to be around positive people.
تعرفون, انته عليكم ان تحيطوا أنفسكم بالأشخاص الإيجابين
I mean, like even when I told my wife that you want to come out here
اقصد, عندما اخبرت زوجتي انك اردتي القدوم إلى هنا
and talk to me, she's like, 'She's just talking;
لمقابلتي, قالت لي انها فقط تتحدث
she's just being nice to you. She's not going to do that.'
انها فقط تحاول ان تكون لطيفة معك, لكنها لن تقوم بذلك
"And then you called me up and you said you wanted to come out here
ثم هاتفتيني, واخبرتني انكي تودين القدوم
and interview me and she went and looked you up on the Internet.
ومقابلتي, فذهبت وبحثت عنك في الإنترنت
She said, 'Look who she is.
اخبرتني انظر من هي
You're not even going to be able to answer her questions.'
ليس بإمكانك حتى الإجابة على اسئلتها
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And she was saying you're going to make me look like an idiot
واخبرتني انك ستجعلينني ابدو كالأبله
because I've never been to college,
لأنني, لم اذهب قط للجامعة
and I wouldn't be talking professional or anything.
و ليس بإمكاني الحديث بإحتراف او اي شيء
I said, 'Well look, the woman talked to me for four hours.
قلت لها انظري المرأة تحدثت الي لفترة أربعة ساعات
You know, if I wasn't talking -- you know,
تعرفين, إذا لم اكن اتحدث - كما تعلمين
like, you know, she wanted me to talk,
كما تعلمين لقد ارادتني ان اتحدث
I don't think she would even come out here.'
لا أظن حتى انها ستأتي إلى هنا
"Confidence? Well, I think I ride
ثقةً؟ حسنًا اظن انني امتلك
more out of determination than confidence.
اصرارًا اكثر من الثقة
I mean, confidence is like, you know,
اعني, ان الثقة كما تعلمين
you've been on that bull before; you know you can ride him.
أن تحس انك على ذلك الثور حتى قبل ان تركبه
I mean, confidence is kind of like being cocky, but in a good way.
اقصد, انها ثقة تجعلك متعجرفًا لكن بطريقة جيدة
But determination, you know, it's like just, you know, 'Fuck the form,
لكن الإصرار, كما تعلمون, انه فقط كمقولة
get the horn.'
" اعبث مع الثور سيتوجب عليك اخذ الطعنة "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's Tuff Hedeman, in the movie '8 Seconds.'
كــــتاف هيدمان, في عرض ال8 ثواني
I mean, like, Pat O'Mealey always said when I was a boy,
اقصد كبات اوميلي عندما كنت صبيًا حدثنا
he say, 'You know, you got more try than any kid I ever seen.'
تعلم, لديك دافع للمحاولة اكثر من اي صبي شاهدته
And try and determination is the same thing.
والدافع للمحاولة والإصرار هاهنا نفس الشيء
Determination is, like, you're going to hang on that bull,
الإصرار, كما تصر على ركوب الثور بأية طريقة
even if you're riding upside down.
حتى وإن ركبته رأسًا على عقب
Determination's like, you're going to ride
الإصرار, كما لو أنك ستستمر في الركوب
till your head hits the back of the dirt.
حتى ولو ارتطم راسك بالتراب
"Freedom? It would have to be the rodeo.
الحرية؟ هي مصارعة الثيران
"Beauty? I don't think I know what beauty is.
الجمال؟ لا أعلم معنى الجمال
Well, you know, I guess that'd have to be the rodeo too.
طيب, تعرفين, اعتقد انها مصارعة الثيران أيضًا.
I mean, look how we are, the roughy family,
اقصد, انظري إلينا نحن عائلة مترابطة
palling around and shaking hands and wrestling around me.
نتسكع, نصافح ايداينا, ونتصارع في الجوار
It's like, you know, racking up our credit cards on entry fees and gas.
كما تعلمين, نبعثر حسابات إئتماننا على المصاريف والبنزين
We ride together, we, you know, we, we eat together
نركب سوية, وكما تعلمين نأكل سوية.
and we sleep together.
وننام سوية
I mean, I can't even imagine what it's going to be like
اعنني انني لايمكن ان اتخيل كيف سيكون اليوم الأخير
the last day I rodeo. I mean, I'll be alright.
الذي سأصارع فيه الثيران, اقصد, سأكون بخير
I mean, I have my ranch and everything,
اعني ان لدي مزرعة و كل شيء
but I actually don't even want to think the day that comes.
ولكن حقيقتًا لا أريد ان اتخيل قدوم ذلك اليوم
I mean, I guess it just be like --
اعني, اظن انه سكيون فقط كـــ--
I guess it be like the day my brother died.
اظن انه سيكون كاليوم الذي توفي فيه اخي
"Toughness? Well, we was in West Jordan, Utah, and this bull
قسوة؟ حسنًا كنا في ويست جوردان, يوتا, وهذا الثور
shoved my face right through the metal shoots in a --
شق وجهي تمامًا كما لوكانت طلقات رصاص
you know, busted my face all up and had to go to the hospital.
كما تعرفين اصاب كامل وجهي بالكدمات واضطررت للذهاب للمستشفى
And they had to sew me up and straighten my nose out.
واحتاجوا لأن يخيطوا وجهي, ويصلحوا انفي
And I had to go and ride in the rodeo that night,
واضطررت للذها ب والركوب مرة اخرى داخل الحلبة في تلك الليلة
so I didn't want them to put me under anesthesia,
إذَا لم أسألهم ليقوموا بتخديري
or whatever you call it. And so they sewed my face up.
او اي شيء من هذا القبيل, وقاموا بخياطة وجهي
And then they had to straighten out my nose,
وبعدها اضطروا لتقويم انفي
and they took these rods and shoved them up my nose
واخذوا تلك القضائب ووضعوها داخل انفي
and went up through my brains
حتى وصلت الى دماغي
and felt like it was coming out the top of my head,
حتى احسست انها ستخرج من فوق رأسي
and everybody said that it should have killed me,
حتى ان كل شخص قال انها لابد ان تقتلني
but it didn't, because I guess I have a high tolerance for pain.
لكنها لم تفعل, واظن لأن لدي مقدرة عالية على تحمل الألم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But the good thing was, once they shoved those rods up there
لكن احسن شيء, وقت ان ادخلو تلك القضائب
and straightened my nose out, I could breathe,
وقوموا لي انفي استطعت ان اتنفس
and I hadn't been able to breathe
لم استطع التنفس من قبل
since I broke my nose in the high school rodeo."
لم استطع التنفس منذ ان كسرت انفي في احدى صراعات الثيران في المدرسة
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)